<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Ad generalem sessionem pacis pro comitatu prædicto tent. apud Chelmisford in dicto comitatu die Martis quinto die Octobris anno regni Domini nostri Caroli ... whereas the Lords of His Majesties most honourable Privie Councell by His Highnesse expresse direction have by their severall letters commended unto us severall instructions ...</title>
            <author>Essex (England)</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1630</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 14 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 5 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A00404</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 10533.7</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S2660</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">24470756</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 24470756</idno>
            <idno type="VID">27701</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A00404)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 27701)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1851:15)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Ad generalem sessionem pacis pro comitatu prædicto tent. apud Chelmisford in dicto comitatu die Martis quinto die Octobris anno regni Domini nostri Caroli ... whereas the Lords of His Majesties most honourable Privie Councell by His Highnesse expresse direction have by their severall letters commended unto us severall instructions ...</title>
                  <author>Essex (England)</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>7 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>W. Jones,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[S.l. :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1630]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>T.p. lacking?; second part of title from first five lines of text.</note>
                  <note>Signed at end: Per Richardum Dove clericum pacis.</note>
                  <note>Imprint suggested by STC (2nd ed.).</note>
                  <note>Orders by the justices of peace concerning alehouses, and rogues and vagabonds and scarcity of corn.</note>
                  <note>Imperfect: torn, with some loss of print.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Harvard University. Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Essex (England) --  History.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-11</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-11</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:27701:1"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:27701:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>Ad generalem Seſſionem pacis pro Comitatu praedicto tent. apud Chelmiſford in dicto Comitatu die Martis Quinto die Octo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bris Anno Regni Domini nostri Caroli Deigratia, Angliae, Scotia, Franeiae, &amp; Hiberniae Regis fidei defenſor is, &amp;c. Sexto. Coram Roberto Comite Warr. Gulielmo Domino Maynard, Harbottello Grimſton milite &amp; Baronetto, Thoma Cheeke mil. Henrico Mildmay de Moulſham mil. Nicholao Coote mil. Thoma Wiſeman mil. Henrico Mildmay de Graces mil. Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thuro Herris mil. Gulielmo Maxey mil. Humfreydo Mildmay mil. Thoma Fanſhaw mil. Drugone Deane mil. Gulielmo Towſe Iohanne Darcy, Iohanne Brampston ſervientibus ad legem, Roberto Aylet Iuris Civilis Doctore, Henrico Gent, Martino Lumley, Iohanne Wright, Iohanne Argall, Roberto Wiſeman, Iacobo Heron, &amp; ſocijs ſuis Iuſticiarijs dicti Domini Regis ad pacem in dicto Com. conſervand. Nec non ad diverſas felonias, &amp;c. audiend. &amp; terminand. aſsignat. inter alia ordinat. est ut ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quitur.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>HEREAS the Lords of his Majeſties moſt honourable Privie Councell by his Highneſſe expreſſe direction have by their ſeverall Letters commended unto us ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall inſtructions tending to the preventi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the ſcarcity and dearth of Corne, and other Victuall, and to the abatement of the price thereof, already growne to very great and high rates, with ſpeciall charge to put the ſaid inſtructions in exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution within all the parts of this County. It is thereupon, and for the reformation of ſome other abuſes tending to the gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall and publicke prejudice and grievance of this County, or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered.</p>
            <pb n="2" facs="tcp:27701:2"/>
            <p>FIrſt, that the Iuſtices of peace of every diviſion within this County do with al convenient ſpeed before the next Quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Seſſions meet together, and doe ſo meet and aſſemble them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves once at the leaſt betweene every Quarter Seſſions, to enquire, and take care, and courſe for the due execution of the ſeverall Articles hereafter following, and of all ſuch other di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rections as we ſhall hereafter receive from his Majeſty, or from the Lords of his Privy Councell.</p>
            <p>SEcondly, that the ſaid Iuſtices of peace at their firſt mee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting do ſuppreſſe the third part at the leaſt of the Ale-houſes within every ſeverall diviſion: It being conceived both by his Majeſty and the Lords of his Councell, and ſo intimated to us by the ſaid Letters, that the great number of Ale-houſes is a very great waſt and conſumption of Malt, already growne to an extreame price.</p>
            <p>THirdly, that no Inne-keepers, or Ale-houſe-keepers doe permit or ſuffer any the Inhabitants, in, or neere unto the Pariſhes where the ſaid Innes or Ale-houſes are ſcituate, to ſit drinking or tipling in their houſes contrary to the lawes in that caſe made, and provided: the true uſe of Innes and Ale-hou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes being to entertaine paſſengers and travellers, and not for the maintenance of riot and drunkenneſſe.</p>
            <p>FOurthly, that no Inne-keepers, Ale-houſe-keepers, or Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctuallers be permitted to ſell leſſe than one full Ale-quart of the beſt Ale, or Beere, and two quarts of the ſecond ſort for a penny upon penalty of twenty ſhillings for every default, which defaults are diligently to be enquired after, and care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully to be levied and diſpoſed to the uſe and reliefe of the poore of the Pariſh where ſuch defaults ſhall be made accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the Law in that behalfe eſtabliſhed. And for the better
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:27701:2"/>obſervation thereof it is further ordered that no Brewer, Inne-keeper, Ale-houſe-keeper, or Victualler be permitted to brew any Beer or Ale of greater ſtrength than according to two bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhels of Malt to one hogſhead at the moſt.</p>
            <p>FIfthly, that all ſuch as ſhall keepe unlicenced Ale-houſes, or ſhall uſe their Innes as Ale-houſes to the maintenance of exceſſe and riot in drinking, be from time to time complai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned of unto the Iuſtices of peace next adjoyning, and that ſuch Iuſtices of peace upon ſuch complaint, and due proofe there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, doe forthwith execute the penalty of the Law upon ſuch offenders, and that in default of ſuch complaint all ſuch offenders be preſented to the ſaid Iuſtices at their meetings a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foreſaid by the high and petty Conſtables of the ſeverall Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhes within every ſuch diviſion, who are likewiſe to preſent at the ſaid meetings at the furtheſt all and every the offences a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt any of theſe Articles, and condigne puniſhment to be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flicted upon them for neglecting their duties in making ſuch preſentments.</p>
            <p>SIxthly, that the ſaid Iuſtices of peace take ſpeciall care for ſuppreſſing the unneceſſary number of Malſters within this County, and confine the reſidue to ſuch a proportion, as that as much Barley (as with conveniency may) be preſerved for bread corne in this time of ſcarcitie of corne, and the penal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties to be duely levied upon all ſuch Malſters as ſhall not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme themſelves therein according to the lawes in that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>halfe provided.</p>
            <p>SEventhly, that the ſaid Iuſtices of peace within their ſeveral diviſions doe take ſpeciall care and order from time to time to have the Markets well ſupplied with Corne, and other Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctuall, and to uſe the beſt indeavour they lawfully may for the
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:27701:3"/>abating of the price thereof, eſpecially that the poorer ſort of people may have graine and other victuall at as eaſie rates and prices as can lawfully be procured. And that they with all <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>are and diligence prevent and hinder all tranſportation, fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtalling, engroſſing, and regrating of Corne, and other victu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all, and to puniſh all offenders therein, by inflicting upon them the uttermoſt penalties which by law they can.</p>
            <p>EIghtly, that there be ſpeciall care had that Millers doe not take exceſſive toll, but that the offenders therein be care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully enquired after, and duely preſented to the Iuſtices at their meetings aforeſaid for ſuch courſe to be taken for reformation of that abuſe as ſhall be agreeable to law and iuſtice.</p>
            <p>NInthly, that no Rogues, Vagabonds, or other looſe, idle or diſſolute perſons, either Engliſh or Iriſh, be ſuffered to begg, or wander, within any part of this County, but that as well the lawes for puniſhing them, as for inflicting penal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties upon ſuch as ſhall relieve them, or upon the Conſtables for not puniſhing them, be duely obſerved and put in executi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. And that the petty Conſtables doe whip and ſend away by paſſes with guides to the place of their birth or laſt ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling according to the lawes, the ordinary ſort of the ſaid Rogues, looſe, idle, and diſſolute wandring perſons, and ſuch as are Iriſh, to puniſh and ſend them away by guides and paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes as aforeſaid unto the next Port for their tranſportation in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Ireland according to his Majeſties late Proclamation in that behalfe. And that the ſaid Conſtables doe apprehend &amp; carry all ſuch of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> as wander under the name of ſouldiers or mariners, or ſhall appeare to be fearfull or dangerous to the inferiour ſort of people, before ſome, or one of the next Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtices of the peace to be further proceeded againſt according to the Law: And becauſe the remiſneſſe and negligence of
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:27701:3"/>the ſaid petty Conſtables is generally obſerved to be a ſpeciall cauſe of the ſwarming of Rogues in all parts of this County, the high Conſtables are ſpecially required within their ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall diviſions to take care thereof, and from time to time to enquire of ſuch defaults of the ſaid petty Conſtables, and of ſuch as ſhall relieve the ſaid Rogues contrary to the Law, and to informe the next Iuſtices of peace thereof, and to preſent the ſame at the furtheſt to the Iuſtices at their ſaid ſixe weeks mee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings. And that the ſaid Iuſtices of peace doe at their ſaid meetings exact a ſtrict account thereof from the ſaid high Conſtables of their care and proceedings therein, the rather for that thoſe Rogues and wandering perſons doe now in this time of ſcarcity eat up the bread of the true poore Inhabitants by preventing them of that charity which otherwiſe would be afforded to them.</p>
            <p>TEnthly, for the better execution of the Lawes againſt the ſaid Rogues, and other wandering perſons, the high Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtables within every diviſion are to appoint watches in the night, and wardings in the day for the apprehenſion of the ſaid Rogues, and other wandering perſons; this to be done at ſuch times and places as the ſaid high Conſtables ſhall thinke fitteſt for the apprehenſion of them. And the ſaid high Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtables are alſo once every moneth at leaſt to cauſe privie ſear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches to be made in every Pariſh within their ſeverall diviſions for apprehenſion and puniſhment of the ſaid offenders.</p>
            <p>ELeventhly, the high and petty Conſtables are to preſent to ſaid Iuſtices of peace at their ſaid fixe weekes meetings, and to cauſe then to be brought before them all ſuch young men and women being unmarried as live at their owne hands out of ſervice, and others though married, and houſholders that live idly, or will not worke for reaſonable wages, or that
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:27701:4"/>waſt, and conſume in riot, drinking or play, what they get by their worke, ſuffering their wives and children in the meane time to be pinched with want of foode, and other neceſſaries, and when ſickneſſe, age or death commeth, then leave their wives and children to the charge of the Pariſh.</p>
            <p>LAſtly, becauſe the high wayes within this County are in great decay, occaſioned principally by the neglect of the workes appointed by the Law both with labourers and Carts, and by not ſcouring the ditches adjoyning to the ſaid high wayes, and the water-courſes for conveying the water out of the ſaid ditches, and by not lopping and cutting the trees, and buſhes adjoyning to the ſame high wayes. It is ordered, that the Iuſtices of peace within every diviſion doe take ſpeciall care for the cleanſing and ſcouring of all the ſaid ditches, and water-courſes, eſpecially ſuch as adjoyne unto the great and high Roades: and for the ſpeedy carrying away of all ſuch earth as ſhall be throwne into the high wayes out of any ſuch ditches or water-courſes. And becauſe many are this yeare behinde with their workes, ſome with labourers, and others with carts, whereof ſome have beene preſented at this Quarter Seſſions. It is now ordered, that all the Surveyours of the high wayes within this County which have not already pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented the defaults in the ſaid workes, doe at the next Quarter Seſſions of the peace to be holden for this County, make a juſt and true preſentment of all ſuch defaults within their ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall precincts, and in default of ſuch preſentment the penalty of forty ſhillings to be inflicted upon every ſuch Surveyour for not preſenting ſuch defaults unto the next Iuſtice of the peace according to the Law in that behalfe provided. And that the Iuſtices of peace within their ſeverall diviſions doe by their owne view informe themſelves before the ſaid next Quarter Seſſions of all defaults in not ſcouring the ſaid ditches
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:27701:4"/>and water-courſes, in not carrying away the earth throwne out of the ſaid ditches into the high-wayes, and in not lopping and cutting the trees and buſhes in or adjoyning unto the ſame: and that the Iuſtices doe at the ſaid next Quarter Seſſions pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent all ſuch offences (as upon their owne view) that the offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders may be puniſhed according to the Law.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Per Richardum Dove Clericum pacis.</signed>
            </closer>
            <pb facs="tcp:27701:5"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:27701:5"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
